<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>*JJ</title><link href="https://jdotjdot.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jdotjdot.github.io/feeds/seminar.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jdotjdot.github.io/</id><updated>2014-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>I gave a Hacker School Seminar</title><link href="https://jdotjdot.github.io/2014/04/i-gave-a-hacker-school-seminar/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>JJ</name></author><id>tag:https://jdotjdot.github.io,2014-04-29:2014/04/i-gave-a-hacker-school-seminar/</id><summary type="html">&lt;!-- 4/29/2014 --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today at Hacker School, I gave a seminar entitled &amp;#8220;Freelance and Travel for Fun and Profit,&amp;#8221; talking about the year I spent traveling the world while supporting myself as a freelance programmer.  I&amp;#8217;ve long been meaning to write this up as both a series of blog posts and a full deck to present, so it was great to have the first opportunity to finally present on it.  There was quite a bit of demand for it, and I actually gave the talk in the first place specifically because other Hacker Schoolers kept saying they&amp;#8217;d love to learn more about what I did and how I did&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the time being, I&amp;#8217;ll post some of the notes and such from the talk, and later I&amp;#8217;ll post as a separate series more in-depth on the details of how to think about being a&amp;nbsp;freelancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Workflowy document with the notes I used to present the lecture can be found &lt;a href="https://workflowy.com/shared/c6b889cd-4915-aa61-8a21-ad0242456f62/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The map of my travels throughout that time can be found &lt;a href="http://www.travellerspoint.com/member_map.cfm?user=jdotjdot89&amp;amp;tripid=359618"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, courtsey of &lt;a href="http://www.travellerspoint.com"&gt;Travellerspoint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a great experience giving a talk and getting excellent feedback on it, and it&amp;#8217;s a very gratifying feeling to hear from people that you&amp;#8217;ve helped reshape their thinking.  Looking forward to delivering it again, a bit more refined, to those who missed it and to the alumni who wanted to come but were unable to&amp;nbsp;attend.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackerschool"></category><category term="freelance"></category><category term="seminar"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry></feed>