<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>*JJ</title><link href="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/feeds/tag/dial-up-over-cell-phone.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.jdotjdot.com/</id><updated>2014-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Day 9: It works!</title><link href="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/2014/02/day-9-victory/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>JJ</name></author><id>tag:blog.jdotjdot.com,2014-02-20:2014/02/day-9-victory/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We had a great talk by Mel Chua not long ago about different types of learning, and &lt;a href="http://de.slideshare.net/mchua/edutalk-w2014"&gt;how learning works at Hacker School&lt;/a&gt;.   One of the main things she pointed out at the beginning was that learning at Hacker School is very different than the kind of directed learning that you might find in school - all of us are going to spend a fair amount of time being &lt;strong&gt;productively lost&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that we&amp;#8217;ll be sitting there hacking away at something, having no idea what we&amp;#8217;re doing or how it works, feeling very stupid, thinking we&amp;#8217;re not cut out for this, and then every once in a while, out of&amp;nbsp;nowhere&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;center&gt;It works!&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had one of those moments today, while working on an extremely basic android app to record a call, as part of my efforts on the Dial-Up Over Cell Phone project.  I knew absolutely no android before this and no Java, so it&amp;#8217;s been a lot to pick up at once, especially because android development has turned out to be pretty confusing and not that well designed. I was following the official &lt;a href="https://developer.android.com/training/basics/firstapp/index.html"&gt;&amp;#8220;Building Your First App&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; guide, but I was having quite a bit of trouble with&amp;nbsp;it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while, I managed to get an extremely basic two page (or &amp;#8220;activity&amp;#8221;, in android parlance) app up on an emulator.  Eventually I actually put it on a phone, which felt pretty&amp;nbsp;cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First page of the app:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img alt=""First page of my app"" title=""First page of my app"" src="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/images/Screenshot_2014-02-20-17-51-15.png" width="361" height="643"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, after you&amp;#8217;ve written the message:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img alt=""Writing the message"" title=""Writing the message"" src="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/images/Screenshot_2014-02-20-17-51-27.png" width="361" height="643"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, send the message to the second page:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img alt=""The message was sent!"" title=""The message was sent!"" src="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/images/Screenshot_2014-02-20-17-51-31.png" width="361" height="643"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that was great, but ultimately, the goal of today was to get an app working where I could press a button to record a sound, and then press another button to play it back.  This is to help get me on my way towards an app where I can actually record the voice downlink of a call, which is the painful but necessary first step for my Dial-Up Over Cell Phone&amp;nbsp;project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was having trouble with this all day.  Recording is apparently pretty fraught with bugs in android, and playing back is too. I spent much of the data looking at scary errors like &lt;code&gt;media server died&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;incorrect format for writing&lt;/code&gt; or completely useless errors like &lt;code&gt;prepare() failed!&lt;/code&gt;  So I just kept trying different settings, different audio codecs like using &lt;code&gt;AAC&lt;/code&gt; instead of the default &lt;code&gt;3GP&lt;/code&gt;, looking at the saved audio file itself to see if maybe audio was getting written but the player just wasn&amp;#8217;t working, and then I went back to &lt;code&gt;3GP&lt;/code&gt; and noticed that the filename I was saving as didn&amp;#8217;t match so fixed that from ending in &lt;code&gt;.aac&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;.3gp&lt;/code&gt; and then all the&amp;nbsp;sudden&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;center&gt;It worked!&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had my android app on my android phone, pressed the &amp;#8220;Audio Page&amp;#8221; button to go the audio page, and then pressed the &amp;#8220;Record&amp;#8221; button to record, recorded a sound, stopped the recording, and then pressed the &amp;#8220;Play&amp;#8221; button to play it&amp;nbsp;back!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I&amp;#8217;m only 80% of the way there in understanding why this particular configuration worked and I need to understand in order to go the rest of the way, it&amp;#8217;s those moments of &amp;#8220;aha!&amp;#8221; that make it all worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackerschool"></category><category term="dial-up-over-cell-phone"></category><category term="android"></category><category term="mel-chua"></category><category term="it-works"></category><category term="productively-lost"></category></entry><entry><title>Week 2: Dial-up over cell phone</title><link href="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/2014/02/dial-up-over-cell-phone/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>JJ</name></author><id>tag:blog.jdotjdot.com,2014-02-20:2014/02/dial-up-over-cell-phone/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week, I decided on and started on what will be my first project for a bit, assuming everything works&amp;nbsp;out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Internet over cell&amp;nbsp;phone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thought behind this is that in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt;, we used to have unlimited data plans and limited voice plans, but now things have switched and the carriers mostly force everyone into limited data but unlimited voice&amp;nbsp;plans. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it would be really cool if you could use your &lt;strong&gt;voice minutes&lt;/strong&gt; to access the internet instead of your data connection, essentially transmitting arbitrary data from the internet over an analogue connection&amp;#8212;the same way was done with dial-up modems or&amp;nbsp;fax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference here, though, is that we&amp;#8217;d be using cellular connections, which are a lot more likely to be lossy and/or drop calls than the landlines that used to be used for this kind of&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Getting&amp;nbsp;Started&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got started with all of this yesterday, and by speaking to quite a few people, I was assisted in boiling the overall project down into a basic stack that should cover all elements of what would be necessary for this technology, from the highest-level to the lowest-level&amp;nbsp;layer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compression&lt;/strong&gt;
This would be taking the data pulled from the internet (a web page, a picture, whatever) and compressing it so that I have physically less data to send.  There are many compression algorithms already available, many of which can slice up the data into smaller chunks to be sent out separately like I will have to do, so I will use a library that&amp;#8217;s already built.  &lt;code&gt;LZMA&lt;/code&gt; was recommended to me as a good compression&amp;nbsp;algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transport protocol&lt;/strong&gt;
This is one of the major pieces of this technology that I&amp;#8217;m going to have to design and implement effectively from scratch.  Somehow, I need a way for the sending server to decide how to bundle up the different packets of compressed information and send them one at a time (or more than one at at time) similar to how it&amp;#8217;s done currently on the internet.
It&amp;#8217;s kind of like the way it was sending letters by mail before telephone and internet - the sender would send a letter and would have no way of knowing if the intended recipient received it unless he sent a letter back, as well.  Current internet protocols (like &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TCP&lt;/span&gt;) have this built in in what is called a &lt;a href="http://www.inetdaemon.com/tutorials/internet/tcp/3-way_handshake.shtml"&gt;&amp;#8220;three-way handshake&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; so that the two computers know that they are both sending and receiving.
Super-summarized, if we continued with the letter-sending comparison, it&amp;#8217;s something along these&amp;nbsp;lines:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bob sends a letter to Alice, saying &amp;#8220;Hey!  Did you receive this letter?&amp;#8221;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is called the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; packet, since Bob(&amp;#8216;s server) is asking to &lt;strong&gt;synchronize&lt;/strong&gt; with&amp;nbsp;Alice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alice, if she receives the letter, sends one back to Bob, saying &amp;#8220;Yup, got yours!  Are you getting this one?&amp;#8221;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is called the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYN&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACK&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; packet, because Alice is &lt;strong&gt;acknowledging&lt;/strong&gt; Bob&amp;#8217;s letter and also asking to &lt;strong&gt;synchronize&lt;/strong&gt; with&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Bob receives Alice&amp;#8217;s letter and sends one back saying &amp;#8220;Yup, got yours too!  We&amp;#8217;re in&amp;nbsp;business.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This final packet in the handshake is called the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACK&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; packet, because it&amp;#8217;s just an &lt;strong&gt;acknowledgement&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m basically going to have to do the equivalent of this using tones over a cell phone&amp;nbsp;line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Framing&lt;/strong&gt;
In this layer, I will take the data that the user requested from the internet, and chop it up into little pieces that can be sent individually so that I don&amp;#8217;t have to send it all at once.
This is necessary because it would be too difficult to send all the requested data all at once in one giant package.  One way you could think about it is to compare it to if you had to send the entirety of Harry Potter to someone by mail, and you could only use normal envelopes, because sending by box was too expensive.  Stuffing it all in one envelope isn&amp;#8217;t really practical and could easily get messed up, plus if it gets lost, you&amp;#8217;ve lost everything.   What you would do is but the books up into a bunch of different pieces, stuff them all into separate envelopes, and then send those all out to reach the requester.
However, since they may all arrive at different times, you&amp;#8217;ll probably want to number the enveleopes to make sure that the requester (a) knows the order that they should get put back together in and (b) can tell if any of the envelopes didn&amp;#8217;t make it all the way through, so they can request them from you again.
It&amp;#8217;s obviously more complex than that, but those are the basics behind the transport protocol&amp;#8212;the system of deciding how much to put in each envelope, the numbering of the envelope, and sending, receiving, and acknowledgement of the envelope is all part of framing and the&amp;nbsp;protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Error-correcting Code&lt;/strong&gt;
Hamming code or&amp;nbsp;Golay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symbol modulation&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;QAM&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PSK&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audio&lt;/strong&gt;
4- or 8-bit&amp;nbsp;harmonics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(To be&amp;nbsp;completed&amp;#8230;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackerschool"></category><category term="dial-up-over-cell-phone"></category><category term="tcp"></category><category term="internet"></category><category term="framing"></category><category term="signal-processing"></category><category term="error-correction"></category><category term="compression"></category></entry></feed>