<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>*JJ</title><link href="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/feeds/tag/markdown.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.jdotjdot.com/</id><updated>2014-06-05T19:51:26-04:00</updated><entry><title>Tricking Markdown to let me use ![]() syntax within HTML tags</title><link href="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/2014/06/tricking-markdown-to-let-me-use-syntax-within-html-tags/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-05T19:51:26-04:00</updated><author><name>JJ</name></author><id>tag:blog.jdotjdot.com,2014-06-05:2014/06/tricking-markdown-to-let-me-use-syntax-within-html-tags/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a short post on a technique I discovered to trick Markdown (at least the brand of Markdown that I&amp;#8217;ve been using that comes with Pelican) to let you stick Markdown-style syntax inside of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; tags and have it still be&amp;nbsp;parsed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My particular use-case here was&amp;nbsp;images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TL&lt;/span&gt;;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though normally Markdown doesn&amp;#8217;t parse anything inside of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; tags, you can use Markdown syntax inside of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; tags in a Markdown file by tricking the Markdown using fake &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; closing tags within a comment.  Example below, using Markdown image syntax along with Pelican&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://pelican.readthedocs.org/en/latest/content.html#linking-to-internal-content"&gt;internet content linking&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;syntax:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- &amp;lt;/center&amp;gt; --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;![My Image!]({filename}/images/myimage.png)&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This should render a centered image in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;, properly rendering the Markdown image syntax, like&amp;nbsp;so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- &amp;lt;/center&amp;gt; --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;alt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;My Image!&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;https://myblogurl.com/images/myimage.png.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always stick arbitrary &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; inside a Markdown document, and it will pass through into the final rendered &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; document unchanged.  This is often done for images, because even though Markdown has an image&amp;nbsp;syntax:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;alt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;](&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;http&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;//image-URL/)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most flavors of Markdown don&amp;#8217;t allow you to set the width and height, so people tend to use straight-up &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;alt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;alt-text&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;http://image-URL&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because of difficulties with centering, as long as you&amp;#8217;re using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;, it&amp;#8217;s also easy to center the image using &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags or by using styling, whether in-line styling or adding a class to your image.  Vertical styling can be a pain though, and what I tended to need to do was stick everything inside a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in order to center&amp;nbsp;it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;style=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;text-align: center;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;alt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;path/to/image&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- or --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;alt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;/path/to/image&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;The Problem: Relative URLs and other Markdown&amp;nbsp;syntax&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem that arose in my particular case was trying to center an image while using relative URLs in the Markdown to specify the image source.  In the Pelican docs, there&amp;#8217;s a section on &lt;a href="http://pelican.readthedocs.org/en/latest/content.html#linking-to-internal-content"&gt;linking to internal content&lt;/a&gt; which specifies the following syntax for linking to any internal content within&amp;nbsp;Markdown:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;My&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]({&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;images&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;myimage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;png&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the &lt;code&gt;{filename}/file/path&lt;/code&gt; syntax only works within a Markdown-style image or link tag, and so I couldn&amp;#8217;t use that syntax within an &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag.  However, if I wanted to center the image, I &lt;em&gt;needed&lt;/em&gt; to have my image appear within manually-specified &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags or a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  This posed an issue, as Markdown does not process anything within manually specified &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; tags, so you would run across the following&amp;nbsp;issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Markdown: --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;![My Image](http://image/path)&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- will be rendered in HTML as: --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;![My Image](http://image/path)&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;The Solution: Trick&amp;nbsp;Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a guess and figured that the Markdown parser was relatively lazy and didn&amp;#8217;t take great care when refusing to parse anything within &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; tags&amp;#8212;my bet was that when it encountered an opening &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; tag, it simply stopped parsing until it encountered the close of that tag.  If I was right, that meant I could trick the parser like&amp;nbsp;so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- &amp;lt;/center&amp;gt; --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;![My Image!]({filename}/images/myimage.png)&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And sure enough, it works!  This creates a centered image in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;, properly rendering the Markdown image syntax, like&amp;nbsp;so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- &amp;lt;/center&amp;gt; --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;alt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;My Image!&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;https://myblogurl.com/images/myimage.png.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;A Better Solution for&amp;nbsp;Pelican&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re using Pelican, the better solution ultimately is to use the &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-plugins/tree/master/liquid_tags"&gt;Liquid-style tags&lt;/a&gt; plugin, which should not only let you specify the width and height but also let you stick it inside an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; tag.  You still get to use the relative filename Pelican syntax, as&amp;nbsp;well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;literal&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;}/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;images&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Screenshot_2014-02-20-17-51-27.png&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;361&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;643&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Example image&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, what I&amp;#8217;ve discovered above should remain useful to those using straight Markdown without access to plugins and who don&amp;#8217;t want to have to get creative with their blog theme or&amp;nbsp;Javascript. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pelican"></category><category term="markdown"></category><category term="html"></category><category term="images"></category></entry><entry><title>Static site generators and choices</title><link href="http://blog.jdotjdot.com/2014/03/static-site-generators-and-choices/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>JJ</name></author><id>tag:blog.jdotjdot.com,2014-03-26:2014/03/static-site-generators-and-choices/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TL&lt;/span&gt;;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m undecided on exactly where to settle on hosting my site.  The main things I&amp;#8217;m looking for&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code syntax&amp;nbsp;highlighting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nicely formatted list of categories and full archive on the&amp;nbsp;sidebar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Editing from&amp;nbsp;anywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ease of&amp;nbsp;publishing/deployment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Intro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, my Hacker School blog is hosted on &lt;a href="http://ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt;, and as much as it&amp;#8217;s nice and easy to use with a great online writing platform, my ultimate goal is to be able to write anything from anywhere, and unfortunately Ghost isn&amp;#8217;t going to fit the bill there, by nature of having an online text editor that I have to&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve heard quite a bit about static site generators like &lt;a href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, and I went in to go take a&amp;nbsp;look.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is a static site generator, you&amp;nbsp;ask?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fair question.  Most blogging platforms (like Wordpress, for example) are &lt;em&gt;dynamically generated&lt;/em&gt; sites&amp;#8212;meaning that the page is being generated from underlying data in a database every time you load it.  This sounds more complicated than it is.  Think about a site like Craigslist&amp;#8212;every time you view the same &lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt;, the actual listings are actually always changing and being updated.  This is a dynamically generated site, because the page is changing every time.  And how is it changing?  Even though we&amp;#8217;re loading the same formatting and styling every time, the actual content of the posts to be presented to you on each load is being pulled from a database that lives&amp;nbsp;elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while ago, someone smart noticed that your blog posts are not really going to be changing&amp;#8212;once it&amp;#8217;s published, it&amp;#8217;s unlikely to change.  Even if you edit it, it certainly won&amp;#8217;t be changing every day (hopefully).  As a result, you don&amp;#8217;t need to dynamically create each page each time a user loads&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is a &lt;strong&gt;static site generator&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a program that lets you build all of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; ahead of time and then post only the static, unchanging files.  Using something like this, you can actually serve your blog right out of something like Dropbox!  (And there are a number of offerings that do&amp;#8212;see &lt;a href="http://scriptogr.am"&gt;Scriptogr.am&lt;/a&gt;.)  Generally, you can write your posts in any text editor using Markdown syntax or something like it.  Markdown is a super-stripped down formatting that enables you to simply and quickly write formatted text that later gets translated into &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;.  (Examples: &lt;code&gt;*italics*&lt;/code&gt; makes things &lt;em&gt;italic&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;code&gt;**bold**&lt;/code&gt; makes things &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;code&gt;[This is a URL!](http://www.google.com)&lt;/code&gt; makes things into &lt;a href="http://www.google.com"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;URLS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that you can create and edit posts from anywhere.  When you&amp;#8217;re ready, you save them into your site generators posts folder and run the program, which generates a fully featured site based on your posts&amp;#8217; content and your selected theme, which styles&amp;nbsp;everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jekyll seemed great at first, and I particularly liked the fact that it can be easily hosted on Github Pages without any extra work (or even site generation) on my part, since Github will run the Jekyll page generation for you.  Unfortunately, it only does that for Jekyll, and not for any others, like Pelican.  The other issue I ran into is Jekyll is pretty unwieldy&amp;#8212;and even using Octopress, which sites on top of Jekyll, I still had quite a bit of trouble getting into the meat of it.  After some Googling, I found that I was far from the only Python person having trouble, and you need to have some Ruby skills if Jekyll ever&amp;nbsp;breaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pelican&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next stop was Pelican, which is a static site generator similar to Jekyll, but in Python.  It&amp;#8217;s also a bit tough to set up, but I&amp;#8217;m liking it a bit more, since I have a better understanding of the internals due to it being in Python.   On the other hand, I&amp;#8217;ve still found it a bit of a handful to set up (spent a few hours on it and I&amp;#8217;m not quite there yet!).  Additionally, it&amp;#8217;s still not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8220;edit from anywhere&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;I know that I can create and edit posts in any text editor and offline, but at the end of the day, I&amp;#8217;ll still have to move all of my posts to the contents folder in my blog repo, run the &lt;code&gt;pelican&lt;/code&gt; command to generate the site, and then push the site to the final Github repo.  I can set this all up automatically with Fabric or web hooks, but at the end of the day, it&amp;#8217;s still a little bit&amp;nbsp;annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Scriptogr.am&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scriptogr.am is a very cool hosted static site generator that runs out of Dropbox.  All you have to do is save your Markdown-formatted files to your special &amp;#8220;Scriptogram&amp;#8221; Dropbox folder, and Scriptogr.am automatically loads the files there, runs them through its own site generator using your selected (or customized) theme, and then hosts the site for you.  This is really great because you truly can edit or post from anywhere, as all you have to do is save to Dropbox, and everything happens automatically from there.  You can even publish right to Scriptogr.am from Markdown-editing programs like Mou for&amp;nbsp;Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downside is, given that it&amp;#8217;s a hosted solution, I have quite a bit less control over the blog itself.  I&amp;#8217;m sure I could manage to force the theme to do my will, but it would mean quite a bit of effort messing with the built-in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; themes, and given that it&amp;#8217;s still a pretty small site, there aren&amp;#8217;t that many themes offered out of the box.  I&amp;#8217;m also not totally clear if there&amp;#8217;s an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed&amp;nbsp;built-in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None yet.  I&amp;#8217;m right now between Scriptogr.am and Pelican, but given that I like the ease of use of Scriptogr.am but the control of Pelican, I&amp;#8217;m likely to go with a combined scenario, where I&amp;#8217;ll basically create my own automatically-publishing version of Pelican out of Dropbox.  Basically, what I will do is create a small Heroku instance that will do nothing but listen for a web hook from Dropbox, and upon receiving it, pull all of the files stored in the Dropbox folder, run the Pelican site generator, commit the repo, and then push to Github pages.
Unfortunately, Dropbox doesn&amp;#8217;t currently support web hooks.  Also, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IFTTT&lt;/span&gt; only has support for the deprecated Dropbox Public folder, but it seems like Zapier does have decent Dropbox&amp;nbsp;integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m at this very moment moving the site over to Pelican, and by the time you read this, it should already be there.  Dropbox also just this week announced that they&amp;#8217;ll be &lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/developers/blog/90/announcing-dropbox-webhooks"&gt;supporting webhooks&lt;/a&gt;, which will be very exciting for enabling me to simply manage all of my post content out of Dropbox and then have the site regenerated upon any&amp;nbsp;changes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackerschool"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="jekyll"></category><category term="scriptogr.am"></category><category term="dropbox"></category><category term="zapier"></category><category term="markdown"></category><category term="static-site-generators"></category></entry></feed>